[Music]
great so ethereum in uh 30 minutes so
this is a a presentation that I've given
at I think basically every single Devcon
since launch though I think what's
interesting is how as uh ethereum the
ecosystem uh changes and as ethereum the
protocol changes as the times change uh
the contents also end up changing quite
a bit right so if you go back to the
equivalent of this from 2015 you'll hear
a lot about Uncle blocks of course Uncle
blocks are a feature of proof of work
that we have proof of stake and so we
don't have Uncle blocks anymore now
ethereum also uh of course uh now has a
layer twos and back in
this would not contain layer 2s at all
and now of course as we know layer 2s
are half the story right so ethereum is
above all an evolving ecosystem and uh
the contents of this are going to keep
changing as the technology changes and
also as the emphasis of the uh ecosystem
changes from building basic
infrastructure uh to now also really
putting a huge amount of focus on the
applications so what is ethereum so
first ethereum is the world computer so
who here remembers etherium being the
world
computer this is the place where I'm
supposed to like put that Meme the where
like there's the guy with the gun in
space saying always has been but I don't
know I never understood why you're why
like like giving someone such an amazing
and beautiful Revelation is supposed to
come at the same time as uh shooting
them in space 20,000 km away from home
and so you I'm not going to do that
today so ethereum is the world computer
it always has been always will be uh so
in addition to this ethereum is an
incredibly large and diverse onchain
economy um and uh
fortunately know Josh uh right before uh
well one one skipped before me made an
incredibly good presentation talking
about all of the different aspects of
the economy and also so ethereum is an
incredibly large and diverse Global
community and I and Josh and the uh
automated like intro thing before that I
think did a a really good job of showing
that too so ethereum is many things
right I think uh they're like also Pro
probably you're supposed to like put up
a flashing sign saying e is money as
well but you know ethereum is a lot of
things right and if ethereum is all of
these different things at the same time
so how does the world computer work
right so the way that I think about this
is uh you layer one is the Shust machine
and Layer Two is uh the GPU right so the
layer one of ethereum that is the core
ethereum blockchain this is the anchor
that keeps the rest of the ecosystem
safe and holds the rest of the ecosystem
together layer one is the reason why
layer twos are able to trustly talk to
each other and at least once everything
upgrades to stage two you will be able
to take an asset issue it on optimism
and then move it and hold it inside of a
smart contract on arbitrum and do so
with zero counterparty risk layer one is
not there to be ultra fast it is not
there to do a million transactions per
second layer one is first and foremost
there to be decentralized to be robust
and to be something that is Dependable
Layer Two is the GBU so Layer Two is uh
all of you uh in the in the room who are
part of any single layer two um who here
is part of a layer
two yay who here has used the layer
two who here has used layer
one good it's uh we're all users here so
actually know there's lots of these
different gpus right and ethereum of the
world computer is able to hold together
because each and every one of these gpus
is connected to the trest machine
through optimistic uh proof systems zero
knowledge proofs snarks Starks Bas jolts
plun plunk you know whatever the buzz
words are right uh and uh that all of
these systems actually ensure that ler
one is able to trustly verify what is
going on inside of the layer tws and
layer twos also are able to trustly uh
read what is happening on layer one so
there's an important interplay between
these two components and together they
make up the ethereum that is here today
so what is the L1 it's a chain it runs
proof of stake it doesn't Afra
so it's so what does this me right so
ethere one is uh a chain that has uh
existed alt together for um more than n
years now and it's existed in its
current proof of stake form for um a
little bit over two years and I think
one of the really important things for a
Bas layer to have is you want to have
clear evidence that that you're building
on a base layer that is decentralized
that is open that is robust and that is
likely to keep those traits going
forward into the future right and one
one part of that of course is so like
something that is slow to change right
one part of that is being something that
is not suddenly going to wake up on a
Tuesday have new management and then
suddenly decide that it's just like
totally going to like start deleting a
whole bunch of applications change its
entire model and do other push the fees
up by a factor of 10 and do other things
without warning another part of
decentralization and resilience is
actually recovery right so whenever
problem actually starts to arise
actually be able to recover from it and
have some way of actually improving the
qualities of the layer one over time so
over here um this is uh on the left a
chart of Bitcoin proof of work um mining
pools and on the chart if uh on the
right if they in proof of stake mining
pools actually um I'm deliberately being
generous here because uh putting Bitcoin
proof of work mining pools because
before the merge actually ethereum proof
of work decentral uh was even more
concentrated than this right and so what
we see here on the right is you see